原作者名：Scott Manley
视频来源：youtu.be/SPTz7Ig9RQE
原视频发布日期：20200426
字幕翻译/压制：旋火
Hello it's Scott Manley here.
你好 我是Scott Manley
指2020年4月22日Qased火箭
将Noor卫星发射入轨
A few days ago Iran managed to launch a satellite into space
几天前 伊朗成功地将一颗卫星发射到太空
and this was notable because it was their first successful launch in quite a few attempts.
而这次值得注意的是 这是他们在多次发射尝试中的首次成功
The big difference was that this was a launch by their military, the Republican Guard
最大的不同是 这是由他们的军队 共和国卫队进行的发射
rather than their civilian space program.
而不是他们的民用航天计划
There was a lot of similarities in launch vehicle.
在火箭上有很多相似之处
This was officially called the Qased.
它被正式地称为Qased
But the first stage of that is essentially a derivative of the shahab-3 missile
但它的第一级基本上是流星3导弹的衍生品
which itself is based on the North Korean Nodong missile.
本身就是以朝鲜的芦洞导弹为基础的
There's also a version of this that is made by Pakistan.
还有一种是巴基斯坦制造的版本
But they are all basically an upgraded Scud with an engine which is about 40% bigger.
但它们基本上都是升级版的飞毛腿导弹 引擎比它大40%左右
Now the engine isn't simply a scaled up Scud engine as far as we know.
现在据我们所知 这个发动机并不是简单地放大了的飞毛腿发动机
It turns out that this engine was developed in the Soviet Union
原来这种发动机是在苏联研制的
and probably traveled to North Korea along with Soviet scientists after the end of the Cold War.
并可能在冷战结束后与苏联科学家一起前往了朝鲜
Either way it's estimated that it produces maybe about 30 tons of thrust.
无论如何 估计它产生的推力大概有30吨
Steering is through a vane system in the fuel outlet.
矢量推进是通过喷管末端的燃气舵来进行的
Now as for what the propellant is used.
那么至于推进剂是什么
This is what the exhaust looks like.
这是尾气的样子
And more sources believe that it uses the Unsymmetrical Dimethyl Hydrazine.
更多的消息来源认为 它使用的是非对称二甲基肼(偏二甲肼)
A term which I love to use because it makes me feel smarter.
这样说全称可以让我显得很聪明
And something called AK27 which is believed to be 27% Dinitrogen Tetroxide and the rest is Nitric Acid.
还有一种叫AK27的东西 也就是27%的四氧化二氮 其余的是硝酸(发烟硝酸的一种)
If it was using a hundred percent Nitrogen Tetroxide,
如果是用百分之百的四氧化二氮
we would probably see the characteristic orange smoke.
我们可能会看到特有的橙色烟雾
We don't see that.
但我们没看到
It's brown instead which leads us to believe there's the lower concentration.
而且是橙色的 这说明可能是更低浓度的情况
This is of course social media video supposedly showing recovered debris from the first stage
而这当然是流传在社交媒体上的视频 据称是一级火箭上回收到的残骸
that obviously the first stage broke up.
很明显 一级火箭(的残骸)解体了
This engine, we don't know for sure, but this is roughly the right size.
这台发动机 我们还不确定 但尺寸大致正确
It looks like every other engine we've seen and I mean this is very clearly a rocket engine.
它看起来像我们见过的所有其他引擎 我是指很明显这是一个火箭引擎
It's roughly the right size.
它的大小差不多
It has the regeneratively cooled chamber.
它有一个再生冷却燃烧室
You can see the injector plate which matches existing debris that we found
你可以看到喷注器板 这与我们发现的现有碎片(尺寸)相吻合
and I believe it's in the correct place.
我相信它是放置在正确的地方
The facility where they've been doing this testing is Shahrud
测试设施所在的位置是沙赫鲁德
and the place where the debris was found is
而发现碎片的地点则是在
yeah right in line with where the orbit would have expected to be based upon the orbital elements.
是的 就在基于轨道元素计算出的预期轨道的下方
Now it did launch from a mobile launch vehicle but it was from a facility where they'd been doing testing.
那么 它确实是由移动载具发射的 但这也是他们一直进行测试的地方(而没有进行转运)
Also I note that (at) the door there there is a little plastic lawn chair that they're using for their launch center.
另外我还注意到(在)发射中心门口有一个小塑料草坪椅
I'm not sure if there was actually somebody in there pushing a button.
我不确定那里是否真的有人在按下按钮
But if they were then during the launch you actually see that the door blows open.
但如果他们在里面 那么在发射过程中 你就会看到门被炸开了 (应该会很糟糕吧)
So I'm not sure the person cared about the quality of their plastic garden chair.
所以我不确定那个人是否在乎他们的塑料花园椅的质量
After all he did decide that plastic garden chairs were perfectly good for the VIPs as long as they were blue.
毕竟他确实决定了塑料花园椅只要是蓝色的 就完全可以给VIP使用
Anyway the initial drone images actually tell us a lot about the dimensions and size
总之最初的无人机画面其实告诉了我们很多关于尺寸和大小的信息
and it's very much consistent with being a Shahab-3 derivative.
而且它非常类似于流星3的衍生品
You know the drone flies around gives us lots of different angles, lots of information.
飞来飞去的无人机给了我们很多不同的角度 很多信息
Also note this shot is reverse because that person is walking backwards.
另外请注意这个镜头是倒放的 因为那个人是倒着走的
But that shot did give us a good look at the mission patch
但是这个镜头确实让我们看到了任务徽章的样子
and from that we can see it's pretty much a 6U CubeSat with solar panels
从这一点我们可以看出 这差不多是一个带有太阳能电池板的6U立方星
and it's observing Saudi Arabia and Israel.
并且它正在观察沙特阿拉伯和以色列
There was a tweet by General Jay Raymond from Space Force who identified as a 3Us CubeSat
而在美国太空军的Jay Raymond将军的推特里 他确认是3U立方星
but I'm gonna presume that is a mistake.
我要假设这是一个错误
It's a mistake either this. He stated the wrong thing.
比如他说错了
Or he's accidentally revealed that Space Force can tell the difference between a 6U and a 3U CubeSat.
或者是他不小心透露了美国太空军可以分辨6U和3U的立方星的区别
Anyway we will talk more about the satellite in a bit.
总之 关于卫星的问题 我们稍后再谈
But what I want to talk about is the most interesting part of this mission.
但我想说的是这次任务中最有趣的部分
It's not the satellite.
不是卫星
It's not the booster.
也不是助推器
It's the second stage.
而是二级
The second stage is something which I believe is kind of new for Iran.
伊朗人研发了全新的二级
So yeah we get the staging. I don't know how fast it's going.
所以 是的 我们看到了分级画面 我不知道它的速度有多快
But it's up high enough that it's outside the atmosphere.
但它的高度足以让它处在大气层外
And then the second stage kicks in.
然后二级就开始运行了
The second stage is almost certainly a solid rocket motor based on a new design.
二级火箭几乎可以肯定是使用了从头制造的固体火箭发动机
The infrared camera shows us it's a solid motor because you can see a glow
红外相机显示这是一个固体发动机 因为可以看到光晕
and you generally can't see that unless you have particles in the exhaust
光晕一般意味着尾气里有颗粒
So this solid booster is known as Salman and they actually announced it earlier in the year.
这个固体助推器被称为萨尔曼 他们实际上在今年早些时候公布了它
We have test footage showing it demonstrating its thrust vectoring technology.
测试片段展示了它的推力矢量技术
This test doesn't have a nozzle extension because it's being performed at sea level.
这个测试没有喷管延伸 因为它是在海平面上进行的
We also have like interviews and presentations showing this piece of hardware
还有一些采访和演讲 展示了这个设备的情况
and they're rightfully proud of this.
当然 他们对此也很自豪
This is a much more high-tech piece of hardware than that first stage booster.
相比于一级火箭 这是一个相对高科技的设备
You can see the nozzle extension, the thrust vectoring hardware.
你可以看到喷管延伸段和推力矢量的设备
They explained that this is a filament wound carbon fiber casing.
他们解释说这是一个碳纤维缠绕外壳
So now you've seen that isolated.
那么现在你单独地看过二级了
It's easy to see where it is on the rocket with the fairing sitting on top of it
也就很容易看到它在火箭上的位置 整流罩就在它上面
and the interstage adapter to the rest of the rocket below that.
而它下面则是级间适配器以及火箭的其他部分
The nozzle extends down into that.
喷管延伸到那下面
And when of course you see the video, it's really obvious.
当然 当你看到视频时 它真的很明显
And while people have been measuring this and estimating the performance,
而当人们还在测量这个并估计性能的时候
the video literally goes ahead and includes a screen shot which shows us the performance and everything.
视频直接往前走了 包含一个屏幕的镜头 这向我们展示了性能以及其他东西
So what do we see here.
那么 我们在这里看到了什么
Well the first thing is on the right,
那么首先是右边
we actually get a whole bunch of numbers telling us where the spacecraft is.
实际上有一大堆航天器的数据 告诉我们它在哪儿
What we have is T for time.
比如T是时间
(V for) velocity.
(V代表)速度
H is current altitude.
H是当前高度
I believe X is the down range and y might be a cross range coordinate.
我觉得X是轨道水平方向距离 Y可能是一个横向距离的坐标
Ha is height of Apogee and Hp is height of perigee.
Ha是远地点的高度 Hp是近地点的高度
This is before it has achieved orbit because perigee is a negative value.
这个画面拍摄于它入轨之前 因为近地点是一个负值
These numbers indicate that it's still going up towards Apogee
这些数字表明它还在向远地点上升
and then presumably that will be when it fires the third stage.
大概之后就是它启动三级的时间
And elsewhere we can see confirmation of this
在其他地方 我们可以确认这一点
because those graphs in the top right there, there's one of them which appears to show the velocity over time.
因为在右上角的那些图中 有一张图显示了速度随时间的变化
So that's one in the bottom left, you can see that it rises up initially
左下角的那张图 你可以看到它最初是上升的
and then it flattens out during the staging.
然后 在分级时变得平坦
Then the second stage kicks off and raises the speed to as we see about 5.2 kilometers per second.
接着二级启动 将速度提高到我们看到的5.2km/s
And then there's another sort of constant velocity cruise.
随后是另一种恒速滑行
That's where it's rising up towards the apogee
那时它会向远地点滑行
and then that mysterious third stage will light up
然后那个神秘的三级就启动了
and actually if you look at that you can just see that it seems to have quite a steep ascent there.
而实际上你仔细看的话 好像就会看到一个相当陡峭向上的曲线
so I think the third stage is probably relatively powerful
所以我觉得三级火箭推力可能比较大
but we don't actually know what it is.
但我们实际上不知道它是什么
Some but people say this their rash 24 which was designed for the Simorgh I believe
有些人说这是为凤凰火箭研制的rash(?) 24上面级
but that doesn't make sense for this.
但这并不合理
Because they actually tell us in an interview that is a liquid-fueled upper stage.
因为其实他们在采访中告诉我们 这是一个使用液体燃料的上面级
Finally the one other screen I can really understand given that I don't speak Farsi
最后尽管我不懂波斯语 但还有一个屏幕我真的能看懂
is this one which shows 6 thrusters and it appears to show a tank with two separate sections in it.
这个屏幕显示了6个推进器 而且似乎是一个燃料储罐 它有两个独立的部分
So those look like six bipropellant thrusters
所以这些看起来像是六个双组元推进器
that are probably used for attitude control during the cruise phase.
可能在滑行段用于姿态控制
I'm not clear if there's another larger engine that's used for orbital insertion
我不清楚是否有另一个更大的发动机用于轨道注入
but I guess the most interesting thing is the sign
但我想最有趣的是这个标志
that it's a split tank showing that they're using bipropellant reaction control thrusters.
这是一个分体式储罐 表明他们使用的是双组元反推力发动机(RCS)
It's all hidden inside the fairing so we can't really guess
这一切都隐藏在整流罩内 所以我们无法猜测
but honestly it's not that interesting.
但说实话 这并没有那么有趣
The real thing here to look at is their relatively large solid propellant motor.
真正值得关注的是他们相对较大的固体火箭发动机
Because that's really what they've been going for.
因为这才是他们一直追求的目标
That's what they've been developing.
这也是他们一直在开发的东西
And that test stand that we saw earlier.
还有就是我们之前看到的那个试验台
That's the smallest test stand they built.
那是他们建造的最小的试验台
There are several larger test stands which could handle solid motors with thrusts up to 200 tonnes.
还有几个更大的试验台 可以处理推力达200吨推力的固体发动机
So back to the payload.
那么回到有效载荷的问题上
The newer spacecraft has been picked up by amateurs all over the world.
新航天器的信号已经被全世界的业余(无线电)爱好者接收到了
And it seems to be using off-the-shelf you know CubeSat hardware and protocols.
它似乎使用了现成的立方星硬件和协议
The packets have been decoded by some being confirmed
有些数据包已被解码
that it is in the correct orbit that was declared.
其中的信息被确认是它正处于它宣布的正确的轨道上
And yes it does appear to be slowly tumbling right now.
是的 它现在的确在缓慢地翻滚
Many CubeSats do this for the first few days as they slowed things down.
许多立方星在头几天减慢(翻滚)速度时都会这样做
That being said Space Command has characterized this as a tumbling webcam in space.
话虽如此 但美国太空司令部已经将其定性为太空中翻滚的网络摄像头
Then again, any visual system is practically a webcam in space
不过话说回来 任何视觉系统实际上都是太空中的摄像头
compared to the largest satellites that the NRO has put up.
在把它们与NRO拿出的最大卫星进行比较时
But it's not competing with those.
但它不需要和那些大卫星进行比较
youtu.be/zj1CwEqf29U，Scott Manley到访鸽子卫星制造商Planet Labs
It would be competing with the Dove CubeSats
它的比较对象是鸽子立方星
which are 3U CubeSats with that are entirely devoted to imaging.
这是一种3U的成像立方星
And really the problem here is the form factor limits your focal length.
问题在于外形尺寸限制了你的焦距
So they may very well have a camera in there is comparable to the Dove CubeSats
所以他们很有可能在那里安装了一个可以和鸽子立方星相媲美的摄像头
but why wouldn't they just work through some third party to buy access to planets, you know, at data.
但他们为什么不通过第三方购买比如行星实验室的数据呢
And the answer is it's about the rocket.
答案是火箭
It's about demonstrating the launch capability.
这能验证发射能力
The data that they will get from this satellite will very likely be available from public sources.
他们从这颗卫星上获得的数据 很有可能也能从公共资源中获得
But those sources wouldn't be able to demonstrate Iran's launch vehicle technology
但这些资源无法验证伊朗的运载火箭技术
in particular the second stage which we believe is the first step in building larger and larger solid rocket motors.
特别是二级 我们认为这是建造更大的固体火箭发动机的第一步
What I wonder is what this means for their civilian launch program.
我想知道的是 这对他们的民用发射计划的意义
after the all they've had several failures
在他们经历了几次失败之后
and one of which was of course publicized by President Trump
而其中一个当然是由特朗普总统公开的
revealing all sorts of fascinating details about Iranian space program
这条推特揭秘了伊朗太空计划的各种迷人细节
and US spy satellite capabilities in his tweets.
以及美国间谍卫星的能力
I believe the Safir launch vehicle has reached the end of its line
我觉得信使号运载火箭已经结束了它的使命
and the civilian program wants to go with Simorgh but that hasn't had huge successes.
而民用项目想使用的凤凰火箭并没有取得巨大的成功
I don't think Qased will get a great deal of use
我不认为Qased会被大量使用
because of course they're wanting to replace the first stage with the solid rocket.
当然是因为他们想用固体火箭替换掉一级
And if they do that then that will be a very big leap forward for Iran's space technology.
如果他们这样做 那么这将是伊朗航天技术的一大飞跃
I'm Scott Manley. Fly safe.
我是Scott Manley 切记 注意飞行安全
[音乐]
[Music]